Register of the Iosif Konstantinovich Okulich Papers, 1894-1949
Hoover Institution Archives
Iosif Konstantinovich Okulich Papers
1894-1949
99050
Hoover Institution Archives
7 microfilm reels (1.0 linear foot)
Diaries, correspondence, speeches and writings, printed matter, and photographs, relating to agriculture in Russia prior to World War I, White Russian relations with the United States during the Russian Revolution and Civil War, and Russian émigré affairs.
Okulich, Iosif Konstantinovich, 1871-1949
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1999
Biography
I. K. Okulich was born on 13 November 1871 (O.S.). He received his degree in agricultural engineering from the Swiss Polytechnic in Zürich in 1894. In 1896 he began government service in the Ministry of Agriculture, and was appointed the following year as Government Agronomist of the Tomskaia guberniia. In 1905 he was appointed head of the Agricultural Section of the Department of Agriculture in the same ministry, a post he had held as acting director since 1903. In 1906 he was appointed Acting Director of State Property for the Eniseiskaia guberniia (confirmed in this post in 1909), simultaneously serving as Vice-Inspector of the Forester's corps of the Irkutskaia guberniia. The years 1912-1913 he spent in the Balkans as a special agent of the Ministry of Trade and Industry, returning to the Ministry of Agriculture in 1913 as Assistant Director of the Department of Agriculture in charge of the Fishing and Game Hunting Section.
With the onset of the First World War, Okulich became responsible for forage and food supplies for the army within his ministry. In 1916 he was appointed a member of the Council of the Ministry of Trade and Industry and the administrative secretary for the Chief Food Supply Committee (Glavnyi prodovol'stvennyi komitet). Sent on a mission to Siberia in 1917 to increase fuel supplies, he remained there until April 1918, when the Siberian Creamery Union directed him to Great Britain for the purposes of expanding trade. In 1919, he was appointed a special representative of the government of Admiral Kolchak, responsible for financial oversight in the United States, Great Britain and France. In 1920-1921 he continued in this role for the Priamur government, based in Vladivostok.
Following the conclusion of the Civil War in Russia, he spent 1923-1926 in Yugoslavia involved in the timber export business, and then settled in Abbotsford, British Columbia, where he lived until his death on 21 January 1949. In Canada, Okulich devoted himself mainly to farming and journalistic work, writing often for the émigré press on agricultural, political, economic, and other issues concerning Russia and Siberia.
Chronology
1871 November 13 Born, Krasnoiarsk, Russia
1895 Degree, agricultural engineering, Eidgenössisches Polytechnikum, Zurich Entered government service as Resettlement Specialist of the Office of the Irkutsk Governor-General
1897 State Agronomist for the Tomsk region
1903 Director of the Special and Technical Crops Section of Department of Agriculture
1906 Manager of State Properties for the Enisei Region
1911 Financial and trade attaché in the Balkans
1914 Deputy Director of the Department of Agriculture for Hunting and Fishing
1916 Member of the Council of the Ministry of Trade and Industry
1918 Director of the Office of the Union of Siberian Creamery Associations in London
1919 Special Financial Commissioner of the Russian Government for the U.S.A., England and France; Chief representative of the Union of Siberian Creamery Associations in America and Western Europe; Plenipotentiary of the Union of Siberian Credit Unions in North America
1921 Plenipotentiary Representative of the Priamur Government in the U.S.
1949 January 21 Died, Vancouver, B.C., Canada
Scope and Content
This collection consists of the personal papers, correspondence, speeches and writings and collected materials of Iosif K. Okulich.
It contains materials pertaining to the development of Russian agriculture and the cooperative movement in Siberia (particularly in the first half of the 20th century), to the Russian Civil War in Siberia and the Far East, and to the resettlement of émigré Cossacks from China and Europe to Canada in the 1920s-1940s. Also significant are Okulich's articles and collected information about political developments in the Soviet Union and about the Slav question in the 1920s-1940s, and his involvement in émigré life and undertakings, as reflected in correspondence with well-known émigré figures, and support for a number of émigré causes, including the establishment of the Russkoe sel'sko-khoziaistvennoe obshchestvo and Museum of Russian Culture in San Francisco.
Materials relating to family members who are better known under the anglicized surname Okulitch have retained this spelling.
Detailed processing and preservation microfilming for these materials were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and by matching funds from the Hoover Institution and Museum of Russian Culture. The grant also provides depositing a microfilm copy in the Hoover Institution Archives. The original materials and copyright to them (with some exceptions) are the property of the Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco. A transfer table indicating corresponding box and reel numbers is available at the Hoover Institution Archives.
The Hoover Institution assumes all responsibility for notifying users that they must comply with the copyright law of the United States (Title 17 United States Code) and Hoover Rules for the Use and Reproduction of Archival Materials.
Agriculture--Russia.; Canada.; Russia.; Russians in foreign countries.; Soviet Union--Foreign relations--United States.; Soviet Union--History--Allied intervention, 1918-1920.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.; Soviet Union.; United States--Foreign relations--Soviet Union.; United States--Foreign relations.
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1894-1949.; Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Personal papers, autobiographical essay, bibliography of works, educational and service records, identity documents, family correspondence and offprints of published articles by son, Vladimir J. Okulich. Arranged alphabetically by physical form
- DIARIES, 1918-1930.; Box 1
  Bulk of entries from 1918 and 1919, but contains entries and clippings up to 1930
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1924-1949.; Box 1
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1906-1948.; Boxes 1-2
  Drafts and printed copies of articles, brochures, and books, arranged chronologically by title
- SUBJECT FILE, 1918-1948.; Boxes 2-4
  Clippings, correspondence, memoranda, legal documents (contracts, powers of attorney, etc.), reports, and other material collected or produced by Okulich, primarily in the course of his official activities as representative of various governments and organizations during 1918-1922, as well as on Cossack resettlement in Canada (to 1946), arranged alphabetically by subject
- PHOTOGRAPHS, 1894-1938.; Box 5
  Album and individual photographs of Okulich and others
- SCRAPBOOKS, 1917-1949.; Boxes 5-7
  Large-format scrapbooks containing pasted-in personal and service papers (documents, photographs, etc.) and newspaper columns, arranged alphabetically by physical form of contents and chronologically within
- Biographical File, 1894-1949.
  General note
  See also SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, SCRAPBOOKS
  - Articles about or mentioning Okulich (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Autobiographical essay (Folder 2)
  - Bibliography (Folder 3)
  - Correspondence
    - Konstantinov, Petr Filaretovich, 1948 (Folder 4)
    - Morozova, Olga, Includes letter of Vladimir Okulitch to same, 1940. (Folder 5)
    - Okulich, George, 1926 December 20 (Folder 6)
    - Okulitch, Vladimir, 1926-1930 and undated (Folder 7)
  - Curriculum vitae (Folder 8)
  - Educational records, 1894 (Folder 9)
  - Financial records (Folder 10)
  - Materials collected by P. F. Konstantinov. Includes correspondence with Okulich family members (Folder 11)
  - Official documents. Includes diplomatic passport, identity papers, letters of recommendation, powers of attorney and other records supporting Okulich in his official representative capacities, [1918]-1930 (Folder 12)
  - Service record, 1911 (Folder 13)
  - Subject file - Okulitch, Vladimir J. (son). Articles and offprints, 1937-1948 (Folder 14)
  - Miscellany (Folder 15)
- Diaries, 1918-1930.
  - Includes some entries and clipping from, 1929-1930 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Correspondence, 1924-1949.
  See also BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, SUBJECT FILE, SCRAPBOOKS
  - General (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Unidentified, 1935-1946 (Folder 18)
  - Arsenii, Archbishop, Includes letter from Rev. Antonii (Vasil'ev), 1939. (Folder 19)
  - Balakshin, A., 1948 (Folder 20)
  - Bensin, Basil M., See also SUBJECT FILE/Russkoe sel'sko-khoziastvennoe obshchestvo, 1946. (Folder 21)
  - Bogdanovich, V., 1939 (Folder 22)
  - Bologov, G. K., 1946-1947 (Folder 23)
  - Butenko, Vasilii Feodorovich, 1937-1939 (Folder 24)
  - Chavchavadze, Paul, Prince, 1942 (Folder 25)
  - Chazov, Sergei Stepanovich, 1948 (Folder 26)
  - Condrashoff, S., 1947 (Folder 27)
  - Conry, Joseph A., 1939-1940 (Folder 28)
  - Ditchev, P., 1934 (Folder 29)
  - Emel'ianov, Ivan Vasil'evich, See also SUBJECT FILE, 1939. (Folder 30)
  - Fallenberg, Nikolai Fedorovich, 1947 (Folder 31)
  - Frankfurt, Solomon L'vovich, 1940-1947 (Folder 32)
  - Grot, Elena Petrovna, 1947 (Folder 33)
  - Guins, George C., See also SCRAPBOOKS, 1942-1946. (Folder 34)
  - Haensel, Paul, See also SCRAPBOOKS, 1946-1947. (Folder 35)
  - Iankovets [Jankauskas?], P., 1931-1939 (Folder 36)
  - Ignat'ev, Pavel Nikolaevich, Count, 1935-1942 (Folder 37)
  - Karinskii, N., 1947 (Folder 38)
  - Konstantinov, Petr Filaretovich, See also SUBJECT FILE/Russkoe sel'sko-khoziastvennoe obshchestvo and SCRAPBOOKS, 1946-1949. (Folder 39)
  - Krutovskii, Vladimir Mikhailovich, 1924-1936 (Folder 40)
  - Lavrent'ev, Konstantin Ivanovich, 1938-1939 (Folder 41)
  - Mel'gunov, Sergei Petrovich, 1948 (Folder 42)
  - Mel'nikov, Nikolai Mikhailovich, 1925 (Folder 43)
  - Mollov, Ianaki S., 1934 (Folder 44)
  - Novikov, Viktor Kirillovich, 1946-1947 (Folder 45)
  - Pistohlkorz, Eugen von, 1946 (Folder 46)
  - Rogozinskaia, V., 1940 (Folder 47)
  - Sedakov, Boris Vasil'evich, 1938 (Folder 48)
  - Seiatel' [periodical], 1948 (Folder 49)
  - Serebrennikov, Ivan Innokent'evich, 1938-1939 (Folder 50)
  - Shendrikov, I., See also SUBJECT FILE, 1948. (Folder 51)
  - Sirotkin, Vasilii Vasil'evich, 1938-1940 (Folder 52)
  - Sokharev, V., 1938-1940 (Folder 53)
  - Struve, Petr Berngardovich, 1925 (Folder 54)
  - Winterstein, Ernest Ivanovich, 1939-1940 (Folder 55)
  - Zaitsev, Pavel Ivanovich, 1948-1949 (Folder 56)
  - Zarotschenzeff, Mikhail Trofimovich, 1939 (Folder 57)
  - Zarubezhnyi soiuz russkikh voennykh invalidov, 1930-1940 (Folder 58)
- Speeches And Writings, 1906-1948.
  See also SCRAPBOOKS
  - General
    - Notes (Box 1, Folder 59)
    - Newspaper columns, 1921-1939 (Folder 60)
  - "Chistye sorta i uluchshennye sorta, vyvedennye selektsiei iz russkikh pshenits," Holograph, n.d. (Folder 61)
  - "O svobodie soviesti v Sov. Rossii," Typescript (fragment), n.d. (Folder 62)
  - Etude sur la fabrication du beurre en Sibérie occidentale, Milano, Printed copy. Introduction contains Okulich's signature as likely compiler, 1906. (Folder 63)
  - Sel'sko-khoziaistvennyi kredit v Bolgarii, St. Petersburg, Printed copy, 1911. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Liesnoe khoziaistvo i torgovlia liesom v Bolgarii i Serbii, Printed copy, 1914. (Folder 2)
  - Sovremennye politiko-ekonomicheskie voprosy Sibiri, Printed copy, 1917. (Folder 3)
  - Zaprosy vnieshnei torgovli Sibiri, Printed copy, 1918. (Folder 4)
  - "Agriculture in Siberia," World Agriculture, Autumn. Printed copy, 1921 (Folder 5)
  - Vysshee sel'sko-khoziaistvennoe obrazovanie v S. Amerike, Praga, Printed copy, 1922. (Folder 6)
  - "Sibirskii Dal'nii Vostok i liesnaia torgovlia Tikhago okeana," Trudy pervago s"ezda russkikh dieiatelei sel'skago khoziaistva, 1924. Printed copy. For Czech translation, entitled Sibirsky Dalny Vychod a lesni obchod Ticheho Oceanu, Praga, see SCRAPBOOKS/General/"Materialy I. K. Okulicha" (Folder 7)
  - "General A. N. Pepeliaev," Kazach'i dumy, Typescript, 1924 February 15. (Folder 8)
  - "Molochnoe delo," 1928. Holograph and typescript. Includes background notes, clippings and illustrations. Also includes printed material from second edition, Molochnoe delo: Rukovodstvo dlia sel'skih khoziaev, St. Petersburg, and correspondence regarding proposed publication, 1933, 1914 (Folder 9-10)
  - "Ob ustroenii Sibiri," Vol'naia Sibir', 1930. Includes article under same title from an unidentified periodical, Printed copy, 1931 August 31. (Folder 11)
  - "Vzaimootnoshenie Sibiri k Rossii [sic]," Vestnik Obshchestva Sibiriakov v Chekhoslovatskoi respublike, Printed copy, 1931 August 1. (Folder 12)
  - "Vivat Akademia: Proekt organizatsii Akademii sel'sko-khoziaistvennoi promyshlennosti v Sibiri," Holograph and typescript, 1940 August. (Folder 13)
  - "Karpatskaia Rus'," Russkii natsional'nyi kalendar', Printed copy, 1945. (Folder 14)
  - "General A. I. Denikin i evrei," Typescript, 1946 May 10. (Folder 15)
  - "Griadushchee budushchee," Obshchekazachii zhurnal, Printed copy, 1947. (Folder 16)
  - "Ispytaniia emigranta," Russkaia zhizn', 1947. Typescript (missing first page), and printed copy, 1931 December 1 (Folder 17)
  - "Krepostnoe krest'anstvo," Russkii natsional'nyi kalendar', Printed copy, 1947. (Folder 18)
  - "Uspeshnaia sovetskaia rabota," Russkii natsional'nyi kalendar', Printed copy, 1948. (Folder 19)
  - "Zakat nauki v Sov. Soiuze," Typescript, 1948 November 10. (Folder 20)
  - "Muki bolgarskogo naroda, II," Russkaia zhizn', Typescript, 1948 December 26. (Folder 21)
- Subject File, 1918-1948
  - Agriculture--Russia (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Communism (Folder 23)
  - Cossacks. "Pereselenie kazakov," Includes correspondence and printed matter relating to Okulich's activities in assisting the emigration of Cossacks from China and Europe (primarily Yugoslavia and Czechoslovakia) to Canada, 1923-1946. (Folder 24)
  - Denikin, Anton Ivanovich (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Krivoshein, A. V. (Folder 2)
  - Merkulov, Spiridon D. (Folder 3)
  - Russia (Territory under White Armies, Consists of correspondence, clippings and printed matter produced or collected in the course of activities as financial representative of the All-Russian Government (Omsk) and as representative of Priamur Government in the U.S., 1919-1922. Includes correspondence with A. G. Sobolev regarding conditions in the Russian Far East and the activities of the Priamur government, 1920-1922, V. L. Burtsev, A. V. Krivoshein, A. A. Bublikov, I. G. Znamenskii, S. A. Ughet, B. A. Bakhmeteff and others, 1918-1920). (Folder 4-8)
  - Russkoe sel'sko-khoziaistvennoe obshchestvo. Consists mainly of correspondence
    - Bensin, Basil M., Includes related correspondence, notably with I. V. Emel'ianov and P. F. Konstantinov, as well as a typed draft of Bensin's "K istorii vozniknoveniia i razvitii nauki agroekologii," 1939, 1939-1940. (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Konstantinov, Petr Filaretovich, Includes related correspondence with other figures connected with the above organization, 1937-1942. (Folder 2)
  - Soiuz Sibirskikh kreditnykh soiuzov. Includes correspondence and official documents, 1920 (Folder 3)
  - Soiuz sibirskikh maslodel'nykh artelei (subsequently Siberian Agricultural Union). Consists of correspondence, clippings, instructions, legal documents, financial records and other materials relating to the activities of the Soiuz sibirskikh maslodel'nykh artelei (Union of Siberian Creamery Associations) and to Okulich as its representative abroad, Includes materials relating to Okulich's activities in London and France in 1918 and in the United States up to 1924 (liquidation of Boston office of the Siberian Agricultural Union), as well as materials on the Civil War in Russia. Also includes correspondence with I. V. Emel'ianov, A. A. Balakshin, A. N. Chmutin, I. N. and S. N. Shendrikov and others, 1918-1924. (Folder 4-8)
  - Sovet upolnomochennykh organizatsii Avtonomnoi Sibiri. Correspondence, 1930-1936 (Folder 9)
  - Miscellany (Folder 10)
- Photographs, 1894-1938
  - Two photographs of Okulich and one group photograph of the members of the Russkii sel'sko-khoziaistvennyi soiuz, 1938 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Photo album, entitled "Upravlenie gosudarstvennymi imushchestvami Eniseiskoi gubernii, g.," consisting of photographs of people and places connected with Okulich's government service, 1910 (Folder 2)
- Scrapbooks, 1917-1949.
  This series contains a variety of material from each of the above series, pasted into scrapbooks with little regard for order. Some scrapbooks, composed entirely of newspaper clippings, proceed in a generally accurate chronological progression, which is reflected in the order followed below, but most include clippings from earlier or later periods (roughly from 1921). May also include articles by others about Okulich or mentioning him, as well as background clippings
  - Newspaper columns
    - 1921-1939 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - 1935-1939 (Folder 4)
    - Includes photograph of the Okulich summer house in Finland, 1915, and a letter to George C. Guins, 1942, 1935-1944. (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - 1944-1946 (Folder 2)
    - 1947-1948 (Folder 3)
    - 1948-1949 (Folder 4)
  - Personal materials, including photographs, correspondence, official documents, biographical materials and writings by or about Okulich
    - General - "Materialy I. K. Okulicha"
      - Subtitled "K poezdke I. K. Okulich goda." Consists of map of Murman region and photographs detailing Okulich's visit to the area, 1914 (Box 7, Folder 1)
      - Includes his Sibirsky Dalny Vychod a lesni obchod Ticheho Oceanu, Prague, typed autobiographical essay and biographies of children, power of attorney from eastern Russian Cossack hosts and Union of Agronomists and Cooperative Workers of Siberia, 1919, correspondence with A. V. Kolchak, 1919, V. L. Burtsev, 1921, Baroness M. D. Vrangel, 1933, and a large number of his newspaper columns, c. 1940s, 1924 (Folder 2)
      - Includes correspondence, notably with Paul Haensel, D. P. Prianishnikov, 1932-1947, identity papers and service documents, articles by or about Okulich, 1937-1938 (Folder 3)
    - Konstantinov, P. F., "Petrovka i petrovtsy," Russkaia zhizn', 1945 December 27-29 (Folder 4)